Hey everyone, it's Richard. You're
watching the Plain Bagel. Following
months of growing tensions and years of
strikes being exchanged, the US and
Israel carried out a joint attack on
Iran this past Saturday, dubbed
Operation Epic Fury. Uh the stated goal
of the attack was to eliminate the
imminent nuclear threat posed by the
Iranian regime, destroy its ballistic
missile arsenal, degrade its proxy
terror networks, and its navy
forces. However, with the strikes also
killing the country's supreme leader,
Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, and Trump
calling on the people of Iran to
overthrow their government, despite Pete
Hegseth pointing otherwise, it seems
pretty clear that the intent here is a
complete regime change for the country.
And while the initial attack from the US
was very swift, the conflict has very
quickly escalated throughout the region,
with Iran launching a number of attacks
against neighboring countries,
particularly ones hosting US troops, and
Trump suggesting the military operation
could last four to six weeks. Now, in
addition to debates over the attacks,
with many weighing the oppressive and
deadly force that Iranian regime has
been in the region, with the civilian
casualties we've already seen caused by
the US strikes, and the general unstable
nature of the region, one of the stories
we've seen many outlets covering with
this update is how disruptive this
conflict might end up being for the
global economy, which naturally, in the
face of the horrors of war, is not a key
priority here. But there is expected to
be a fairly far-reaching implication
from the conflict that we're seeing.
Which might be surprising for some. Iran
is, after all, a fairly isolated
country. It was, up until 2022, the most
heavily sanctioned country in the world
until it was replaced by Russia
following the invasion of Ukraine. And
the country has long operated as a bit
of a hermit in the region. So, most
would probably anticipate pretty limited
economic fallout from a war in the
country.
But that's actually far from the case.
So, today, we'll go over the risks the
conflict in Iran poses to the global
economy, and why economists are bracing
for pretty far-reaching impact here. Uh
not to make light of the other more
horrific aspects to this development,
but as an economics and finance channel,
I think it's worth diving into the
implications here, and why people who
are even far removed from the region
might see an impact. Now, Iran, as
mentioned, is a fairly economically
isolated country, uh thanks to the slew
of sanctions it faces from developed
nations. The country, an authoritarian
theocracy, was first designated a state
sponsor of acts of international
terrorism by the US back in 1984, with
the country being a key backer of groups
like Hamas and Hezbollah. And while the
country did sign a deal, the Joint
Comprehensive Plan of Action, or simply
the Iran nuclear deal for short, back in
2015 to have some sanctions lifted in
exchange for the reigning in of its
nuclear development programs, the US
itself pulled out of the deal in 2018,
while the United Nations found Iran in
non-compliance back in 2025, leading to
the reimposition of restrictions. With
there long being concerns that Iran is
secretly developing nuclear weapons.
Now, while the UN has focused on more
targeted sanctions, freezing assets for
certain individuals and organizations,
and restricting nuclear and weapons
development, the US has been more broad
with its restrictions, forbidding nearly
all trade, financial transactions, and
investments in the region, beyond
actions authorized directly by the
government, with humanitarian exceptions
only granted for a select few products
like food and medicine. This, combined
with Iran's reliance on oil, has made
the country's economy fairly volatile.
Despite Iran having double the
population of Canada, for example, its
economy is roughly 1/5 Canada's size
when measured in gross domestic product,
with exports likewise being a fifth of
Canada's own. Nonetheless, Iran has
remained a key supplier in the very
important market of energy, in
particular crude oil. Uh you see, Iran
actually produces about 4% of the
world's oil, with the country hosting
the third largest oil reserve in the
world, making up about 12% of global
reserves. And while some of the
sanctions against Iran restrict the
country's ability to sell this oil, the
country has been able to continue
shipping the product thanks to
sophisticated black market channels it's
developed over time. With the country
sending the vast majority of its oil
exports, over 80%, to China, making it
the second largest source of crude for
the country. With an estimated 520
million barrels being sent to China in
2025. Because of this, any conflict with
Iran has historically trans lated into a
jump in oil prices on the expectation of
supply tightening up. And this
circumstance is no different. In fact,
with the attack from the US and Israel,
we've seen the West Texas Intermediate
reach nearly $90 a barrel, up over 30%
over the span of a week. While the Brent
Crude Index has risen 25% to $91 a
barrel. But it's not actually the impact
to Iran's own oil sales that's primarily
contributing to surging prices here.
While that certainly plays a role, most
people have been pointing to another,
more far-reaching variable here.
The Strait of Hormuz. You see, the
Strait of Hormuz is a vital waterway
that connects the Persian Gulf to the
Gulf of Oman. It's where many of the
world's largest oil producers, including
Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates,
and Iran itself, send out their oil to
international markets. In fact, about
31% of all seaborne crude and about 1/5
of global crude oil passes through the
strait on a daily basis. So, you can see
how important the waterway is to global
oil markets. And Iran happens to border
the strait on the northern side,
including the passageway's most narrow
choke point at just 33 km wide. So,
there's long been this concern that Iran
could cut off the world from about a
fifth of its total oil supply. And on
Monday, we saw that risk become reality
when the Islamic Revolution Guard Corps
announced that they would be closing the
strait, warning that it would set any
vessel attempting to pass through a
blaze. With eight vessels having already
been struck in the strait and a number
of shipping companies suspending all
vessel transit and anchoring ships to
avoid attacks, effectively killing
transit in the channel and leaving
hundreds of ships stranded. So, right
away you can see why some are
forecasting a pretty meaningful economic
impact from the conflict in Iran. While
it's true that about 84% of the crude
oil and condensate that comes from the
strait is sent to Asian countries,
including China, India, Japan, and South
Korea, oil prices will likely rise
globally if the closure is maintained as
these countries turn to other markets
for their supply. With a Concaya, a
senior portfolio manager with Newberger
Berman, warning that a disruption
lasting over a month could send prices
well into the triple digits, something
we haven't seen since 2022. As you might
be aware, oil has a fairly broad impact
on global economic activity. Oil is used
for everything from electricity
generation and fuel to the production of
a slew of end products and compounds.
So, beyond the direct impact we can see
on things like gasoline prices, any
increase in oil's price tends to
reverberate across a slew of production
chains. Not to mention that as fuels
become more expensive, it becomes more
expensive to ship and transport goods.
So, even products not directly derived
from petroleum could still see a
meaningful price impact. Now,
importantly, we have to mention that
there are alternatives to the Strait of
Hormuz for transporting Middle Eastern
oil to international markets. As you can
expect, the closure of the strait has
long existed as a threat to the region
given Iran's history and instability.
So, nations have put effort into
developing alternative export routes.
Saudi Arabia, for example, has pipeline
capacity for 5 million barrels per day
that can reach the Red Sea, with this
covering most of the oil the country
exported through the strait in February.
While the UAE has infrastructure that
reaches the Gulf of Oman directly. So,
it's unlikely we truly see 20% of the
world's oil supply just disappear here.
However, with the Red Sea, there's risk
there as well, given that we've seen
Houthi rebels based in Yemen strike
freight vessels in the past, with that
group notably being backed by Iran. The
current conflict has seen some critical
infrastructure damaged in the region,
including refineries, oil storage, a
fuel tank terminal, and Oman's port of
Duqm. With Rystad Energy estimating that
even with these alternatives available,
we could still see crude oil supply drop
by 8 to 10 million barrels per day,
equivalent to nearly 10% of global
supply. So, there's still likely to be a
very meaningful impact. And even beyond
oil, there are a number of other
disruptions that pose threats for the
global economy. Uh the strait is also a
key passageway for liquefied natural
gas, which itself is used for heating,
electricity, and generally as a fuel. Uh
so, disruptions to that commodity will
likewise translate into similar impacts,
with natural gas futures prices having
already jumped over 60% in European
markets. We also see about a third of
the world's urea, a key nitrogen-based
fertilizer, flow through the passageway.
So, this could also have a direct impact
on food prices, with that commodity
having seen its price jump 25% since the
initial attack. The conflict has also
disrupted air travel, with flights being
canceled amid airspace closures in the
Middle East. And marine insurance
companies have already sought to cancel
coverage for war risks related to Iran,
an issue likewise faced by airline
companies, which are now experiencing a
gap in their coverage. Something that's
likely to discourage companies from
operating in the region if they can't
get protection from these catastrophic
risks, with tanker prices already
jumping internationally on the
disruption in the region. And when we
look to neighboring countries in the
region, we of course can expect much
more acute pressures. Many of the Gulf
countries have nationalized their oil
production, meaning that any impact to
their ability to export oil directly
decreases government revenue, which
naturally has broad-reaching impacts for
the country as a whole. On top of this,
war in general tends to contribute to
capital flight, weaker economic
activity, and higher inflation for
nearby countries. And as risks for
operating in the region increase, it's
more likely to discourage that economic
activity. This is especially true for
industries like tourism, which some Gulf
countries are fairly reliant on. The
UAE, for example, derives 14% of its GDP
from the industry. And then there's of
course the more direct risk of capital
impairment, a risk again we're already
seeing play out to an extent with Saudi
Aramco, for example, Saudi Arabia's
state-run oil producer and the largest
oil company in the world having itself
been targeted by drone strikes, albeit
with seemingly no damage to its
infrastructure. So from the acute impact
to the region to the more far-stretching
inflation implications and trade
disruptions, a war in the region is
likely to be highly disruptive to the
global economy even with Iran's
isolation. And if the conflict stretches
longer than anticipated, these impacts
could naturally be quite meaningful.
Using the Kiel Institute's price of war
calculator, for example, which uses 2023
data and assumes an average war that
lasts 3.5 years, we can see that a war
in Iran could cost the country nearly $1
trillion in lost capital, nearly $600
billion in lost GDP, and cause the
economy to contract over 30% all over a
five-year period. While other countries
could cumulatively see a GDP loss of
over $1 trillion.
Now, apparently that's a very crude
estimate that assumes things escalate
far beyond what we're currently seeing.
But given the history of Middle Eastern
conflict stretching well beyond their
initial scope, it is a risk that's faced
here. Now when it comes to the impact on
the US specifically, there's long been
this view that war is actually good for
business as
evil as that sounds. Namely because the
government tends to increase spending
during geopolitical conflicts and
because the US is very far removed from
the devastation of these types of
engagements, some hold the view that
economic activity thrives during wars.
And certainly we have seen periods in
history of GDP growing strongly during
major conflicts. And certain players
will benefit from the current war.
However, even with America's privileged
position, there's still some meaningful
negative consequences to its economy
from these types of engagements. For
one, US inflation tends to spike during
geopolitical conflicts in part from this
higher government spending. Something
that will obviously be more pronounced
here given the impact on the oil market
and the broad disruptions to trade with
freight rates likely to surge and trade
volumes likely to decrease. This may
also lead to an increase in interest
rates. The Federal Reserve is still
grappling with the impacts of tariffs on
price levels and may have to switch to
hiking rates should we see a new
inflation risk. And while US Treasury
bond yields tend to decrease during
geopolitical conflicts as investors buy
the asset as a safe haven investment to
protect their money, we've so far
actually seen yields increase slightly
with fears over inflation seemingly
offsetting this factor. Finally, we tend
to see US debt increase during wars
again because of that heightened
spending, which could prove problematic
given the pressure on interest rates and
the lost tariff revenue the White House
experienced last month from the Supreme
Court's ruling that Trump's IEEPA
tariffs were illegal. I also won't spend
a tremendous amount of time on stocks
given the nature of the situation, but
it is worth noting that while certain
sectors of course experience a range of
impacts during geopolitical conflicts in
the short term, US stock market
valuations in general haven't
historically exhibited a direct
relationship with geopolitical conflicts
over the long term according to the
Institute of Economics and Peace. And
while stocks do tend to experience a
sell-off in the short term, returns tend
to normalize thereafter with performance
often dominated by other variables. All
to say it's not usually wise to trade
off of short-term geopolitical headlines
if you're investing for the long term,
especially given that we just don't know
how things will ultimately settle. Uh
but that's the economic situation with
Iran as it's currently been assessed.
Given that this is a developing story,
obviously many factors are going to be
changing here. The US, for example, has
already highlighted that it'll provide
insurance and escort ships through the
Gulf to combat Iran's closure of the
Strait. So, while that likely won't
offset the full impact, that is
certainly something that could lessen
the blow. And we could see other factors
depress oil prices from here. OPEC plus,
for example, the Organization of
Petroleum Exporting Countries plus other
group participants, recently opted to
raise oil production by over 200,000
barrels per day and could easily push
this level higher should pressure on
supply continue. So, while the group
includes many of the Gulf countries
impacted by the war here, some other
nations may be able to bolster supply
amid the conflict. We also, of course,
have no concept of how long this
conflict might last. We could see other
countries pulled into this like Russia
and China, who is an important lifeline
for Iran. However, the two countries,
while denouncing the attacks, have so
far avoided intervening. But if history
is any precedent, it's likely we do see
things stretch out for some time. And
even if their running regime is taken
down, there's the risk of a power vacuum
forming and other violent groups taking
control. So, a 4-to-5-week time frame
does seem fairly optimistic.
Nonetheless, we'll just have to wait and
see how things develop from here. Uh
thanks for watching. I hope you found
this video helpful. If you did, please
do make sure to like, subscribe, all
that good stuff. It does help the
channel tremendously. And if you're
interested in learning more about how
war generally impacts economic activity,
I'll link to a video that I put out last
year on that topic that you can check
out. Thanks again for joining. See you
in the next one.